Guide to the Andrew Wellington Cordier Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
- Series VII: Andrew W. Cordier Working Papers 1971-1975
  - Berkeley; University of California at: Three Folders of correspondence about AWC's appoint­ment as Regents' Professor at Berkeley campus for Winter 1973-74 term and his seminars and lectures to be held there -1973-74. (Box 284)
  - Biographical Sketch of AWC: Several copies of earlier versions and latest -June 1975 ­curriculum vitae. (Box 284)
  - C-Correspondence with individuals whose surnames begin with "C": One Folder -1972-75. (Box 285)
  - Century Club: copies of a few letters -July-August 1975. (Box 285)
  - Carnegie Endowment for International Peace: One Folder of duplicate material about the Endowment's meetings in 1974 [Awc was Trustee] (Box 285)
  - Centers: Three Folders of correspondence and material relating to several international (off-campus) Centers -1972-75. (Box 285)
  - Columbia University Press releases: Two Folders of mimeographed releases -1972-75. (Box 285)
  - Columbia University -Miscellaneous: One Folder of Financial Reports and other material relating to Columbia University -1972-74. (Box 285)
  - Columbia Presbyterian Medical Center Fund, Inc.: One Folder of one letter and copy of Report prepared for fund raising efforts -1973. (Box 285)
  - Commission of the Churches on International Affairs: One Folder of mimeographed material -1975 (Box 286)
  - Commission to Study the Organization of Peace: Two Folders of mimeographed material-1971-73 (Box 286)
  - Committee on the Future of International Studies: One Folder of several letters and mimeo­graphed material -1972-73 (Box 286)
  - Common Cause: A circular letter-1974 (Box 286)
  - Council on Foreign Relations: One Folder of correspondence and material -1971-75 (Box 286)
  - Crank Letters: One Folder of few letters-1968-72 (Box 286)
  - D-Correspondence with individuals whose surnames begin with "D": One Folder -1970-72 (Box 286)
  - E-Correspondence with individuals whose surnames begin with "E": One Folder-1971-75. (Box 287)
  - Education and World Affairs -Committee on the Future of International Studies: Two Folders of few letters and mimeographed material-1968-71. (Box 287)
  - Environmental Fund -International Conference on Population-Food Crisis: One Folder of several letters, clippings, and mimeographed material-1974 (Box 287)
  - F-Correspondence with individuals whose surnames begin with "F": One Folder-1971-72. (Box 287)
  - Faculty Club: Few memoranda and statements -1975. (Box 287)
  - Foote, Mrs. Wilder (Marcia): One Folder of letters -1975. (Box 287)
  - [Foreign Policy Association: empty) (Box 287)
  - Franklin Books Program and Awards Committee: Two Folders of several letters and duplicate and printed material-1971-73 (Box 287)
  - Fund For Peace -University Consortium for World Order Studies: Three Folders of several letters and duplicate and printed material-1971-73. (Folder 1) (Box 287)
  - Fund For Peace (Folders 2 and 3) (Box 288)
  - G-Correspondence with individuals whose surnames begin with "G"; One Folder-1973 (Box 288)
  - H­ (Box 288)
  - Hanoi-AWC's Proposed Trip to: One memorandum and copies of printed article -December 1972 (Box 288)
  - Hill, Martin: Correspondence-1971-72 (Box 288)
  - Hosni, Dr. Sayed Mohd.: One Folder of correspondence -1967-73. (Box 289)
  - Hughes, Thomas L., President of Carnegie Endowment for International Peace: Copy of his December 10, 1972 speech, II Democracy, Diversity and the Flight from Foreign Policy" (Box 289)
  - I-Correspondence with various groups which names begin with "I": 1971-73. (Box 289)
  - Institute of International Studies (Richard T. Thompson): One Folder of duplicate material-1972 (Box 289)
  - International Development Research Centre: One Folder of information about AWC's attending conference in Ottawa, May 14-15, 1971. (Box 289)
  - International Institute for Environment and Development: One Folder of duplicate material, 1974 (Box 289)
  - International Studies Association: One Folder of correspondence-1972-75. (Box 289)
  - International Marketing Consortium, Ltd. U. Garfield): One Folder of correspondence-1972. (Box 289)
  - Inter-office Memoranda -University: One memorandum and letter regarding use of Room 1425 in SIA by AWC (Box 289)
  - Inter-University Program in Peace Studies: empty] (Box 289)
  - International Association of Universities Conference-Montreal 1970 One Folder of correspondence and material-1969-70 (Box 289)
  - Advanced International Studies -Francis Wilcox: One letter of July 22, 1971 (Box 289)
  - International Center for Theoretical Physics -Trieste: One Folder of correspondence -1971-72 (Box 289)
  - International Development Research Centre: Material regarding May 1971 meeting in Ottawa. (Box 289)
  - J-Correspondence with individuals whose names being with "J": One Folder -1970-73 (Box 289)
  - Japan International Christian University Fund, Inc.: Several letters, minutes, and mimeo­graphed material-1971-75. (Box 289)
  - Journal of International Affairs: Two exchanges of letters in 1973 and 1974. (Box 289)
  - Juanita College: Two exchanges of letters -1972 and 1973. (Box 289)
  - K-Correspondence with individuals whose names begin with "K": One Folder -1970-74 (Box 289)
  - L-Correspondence with individuals whose names begin with "L": One Folder -1970-75. (Box 290)
  - M-Correspondence with individuals whose names begin with "M": One Folder -1971-72. (Box 290)
  - McKinley (William) Visiting Scholar Lectures -in Stark County colleges, Ohio: One Folder of correspondence regarding AWC's proposed lectures -1974-75. (Box 290)
  - Management and Planning Institute for Higher Education: One letter from Thomas P. Ference (Associate Director) of March 9, 1973 to AWC. (Box 290)
  - Memoirs (Box 290)
  - Morehouse, Ward: One Folder of correspondence with and from him and duplicate material-1971-72. (Box 291)
  - McGill, William J. (President of C. U.): One Folder of correspondence with and from him-1971-74. (Box 291)
  - N-Correspondence with individuals whose surnames begin with "N": One Folder -1970-73. (Box 291)
  - North East Universities Consortium: Two Folders of correspondence and materials-1970-71. (Box 291)
  - O-Correspondence with individuals whose surnames begin with "0": One Folder -1971-74. (Box 291)
  - Oral History (Columbia): One Folder of several letters regarding AWC's oral history memoir-1970-75. (Box 291)
  - P-Correspondence with individuals whose surnames begin with "P": One Folder-1971-74. (Box 291)
  - Pace College: Copy of Report on International Business Programs at Pace -1970. (Box 291)
  - Picker, Dean Harvey: One Folder of letters to and from him -1972-75. (Box 291)
  - R-Correspondence with individuals whose surnames begin with "R": One Folder -1970-71. (Box 292)
  - Research Topics: One letter of January 19, 1971 from James R. Morrison. (Box 292)
  - Resumes: Copies of resumes sent to AWC by various people. (Box 292)
  - Rider College: One Folder of correspondence regarding AWC's visit to Rider College, his receiving an honorary degree, and his address at commencement exercises on January 17, 1971 also a copy of his address "Change: Progress or Decay?"-1971-72. (Box 292)
  - S-Correspondence with people whose surnames begin with "S": One Folder -1970-73. (Box 292)
  - *(RESTRICTED) Schuller: One Folder of correspondence with Mrs. Craig Schuller about Erwin Schuller's death (her husband) and the possibility of having his paper "Popular Participation 1n Development in Latin America" published -1968-73. (Box 292)
  - Social Science Research Council: One letter of May 21, 1971 to AWC from Richard D. Lambert, Project Director of Council. (Box 292)
  - SIA Research Program on United Nations Affairs: One letter of November 22, 1974 to AWC from Director, Dr. A. M. Palmer's assistant (Rosaly Anthony). (Box 292)
  - Shaughnessy, D.F.: One Folder of correspondence -1973. (Box 293)
  - Silverman, Jerry: One Folder of correspondence -1972. (Box 293)
  - Soloman, Joseph: One Folder of correspondence -1972. (Box 293)
  - State University of New York: One Folder of correspondence and duplicate material -19 '71. RES'IRJCTED (Box 293)
  - *(RESTRICTED) Schonborn, Dr. Karl: One Folder of correspondence with him and others, and John W. Wheeler (of Thacher, Proffit and Wood) concerning AWC' s "World Without Borders" videotapes and their use in an article about Awe which was printed in the UN Monthly-Chronicle -1974-75. (Box 293)
  - T-Correspondence with individuals whose names begin with "T": 1971-75. (Box 293)
  - Telfeyan, Dr. Sarkis Albert (AWC's doctor): One Folder of correspondence -1972 1975. (Box 293)
  - Tusek-Bronson: Intercultural Program: One Folder of correspondence-1972-73. (Box 293)
  - U-Correspondence with individuals whose names begin with "U": 1970-73. (Box 293)
  - United Nations -General: Several letters dating from December 1971 -July 1974. (Box 293)
  - United Nations-Association of the United States of America: One Folder of correspondence and printed material -1968-75. (Box 293)
  - United Nations Committee for UNICEF: One Folder of correspondence and mimeographed material -1970-75. (Box 294)
  - United Nations Study Group of Democratic Task Force: One letter to AWC from Charles W. Yost -May 23, 1974. (Box 294)
  - Advisory Panel of "Who's Who in the United Nations": One Folder of brief exchange of letters and duplicate copy of working paper for meeting of the Panel -1974. (Box 294)
  - United World Federalists: Copy of the Program of the Fourth Annual Publius Award Dinner of November 21, 1967 at which AWC received the Award. (Box 294)
  - University Club: Records of AWC' s account in 1975. (Box 294)
  - V-Correspondence with individuals whose names begin with "V": -One Folder -1972 (Box 294)
  - W-Correspondence with individuals whose names begin with "W": One Folder -1970-75 (Box 294)
  - Waldheim, Kurt C (Secretary General of U.N .): One Folder of correspondence -1971-72 (Box 294)
  - Ward, Barbara (Lady Jackson): One Folder of correspondence and mimeographed material -1972-73 (Box 294)
  - Woods Hole Oceanographic Institute (Dr. Paul M. Fye): One Folder of brief correspondence and printed material -1971. (Box 294)
  - World Federal Authority Committee: One Folder of mimeographed material -1974. (Box 294)
  - World Studies Data Bank: One letter from AWC to Dr. Leonard P. Iaquinta of December 27, 1973 and mimeographed list of key contacts (names) for international studies at colleges and universities in U. S. (Box 294)
  - Y-Correspondence with individuals whose surnames ,begin with "Y": One Folder -1971-74. (Box 294)
  - Z-One letter of December 27 I 1972 from AWC to Mrs. Guri Zeckendorf (Trygve Lie’s daughter) (Box 294)
- Series VIII: Honorary Degrees, Plaques, Awards and Honors
  - Honorary Degrees (Box 295-296)
  - Plaques, Awards and Honors (Box 297)
- Series IX: Photographs, Printed and Miscellaneous Material
  - Photopraphs -United Nations: (Box 298)
  - Anderson, Marian (Box 298)
  - Ben Gurion, David (Box 298)
  - Bunche, Ralph J. (Box 298)
  - Einstein, Albsrt (Box 298)
  - Eisenhower, Dwight D. (Box 298)
  - Hammarskjold, Dag (Box 298)
  - Hammarskjold (Box 298)
  - Marian Anderson (Box 298)
  - Danny Kaye (Box 298)
  - Hammarskjold, Dag -Album (Box 298)
  - Khrushchev, Nikita (Box 298)
  - Johnson, Lyndon B. (Box 298)
  - Lie, Trygve (Box 298)
  - Kennedy, John F. (Box 298)
  - Roosevelt, Eleanor (Box 298)
  - Nixon, Richard M. (Box 298)
  - Rusk, Dean (Box 298)
  - Paul VI, Pope (Box 298)
  - Stevenson, Adlai R. (Box 298)
  - Thant, U (Box 298)
  - Truman, Harry S. (Box 298)
  - Portraits: Cordier Miscellaneous (Box 298)
  - 1940s (Box 299)
  - 1950s (Box 299)
  - 1950-1951 –Korea (Box 299)
  - 1955–San Francisco (Box 299)
  - 1962-Cordier retirement (Box 299)
  - 1960s-1971 (Box 299)
  - Undated, (2 Folders) (Box 300)
  - Undated -Manchester College Alumni (Box 300)
  - Oesterle, Marie -negatives, contact sheets (1968) (Box 300)
  - Photographs -Columbia Univerity: (Box 301)
  - Albums (with 1 honorary degree) (Box 301)
  - Albums (Box 302)
  - Albums (Box 303)
  - Individuals: (Box 304)
  - Astronauts (Box 304)
  - Bunche, Ralph J. (Box 304)
  - Cordier, Dorothy B. (Box 304)
  - Gandhi, Indira (Box 304)
  - Gish, Lillian (Box 304)
  - Harriman, Averell (Box 304)
  - Lindsay, John V. (Box 304)
  - McGill, William (Box 304)
  - Mead, Margaret (Box 304)
  - Sarnoff, David (Box 304)
  - Shotwell, James T. (Box 304)
  - Stetten, Alice (Box 304)
  - Thant, U (Box 304)
  - Portraits -Cordier (Box 304)
  - Photographs -Columbia University: (Box 305)
  - Academic Ceremonies (Box 305)
  - Alumni Meeting New York (Box 305)
  - Campus, General (Box 305)
  - Excavation and Construction (Box 305)
  - Gates, 1969 (Box 305)
  - Gym Site, 1970 (Box 305)
  - President's House (Box 305)
  - School of International Affairs: (Box 305)
  - 1964-1967 (Box 305)
  - 1969 April, .June, August, October November, December (Box 305)
  - 1970 January, February March -May June-December (Box 305)
  - 1971, 1972 -1974 (Box 305)
  - Miscellaneous Undated Photographs, (6 Folders) (Box 306)
  - Slides (Box 307-308)
  - Tape Recordings (see also: Columbia Hist Records/Films Box 8, "Cordier") (Box 309-312)
  - Typescript Volumes: Cordier, A.W. Southern France After the Albigensian Crusade. 1926 (Box 313)
  - Liebmann, W.B. "Catalogue of the Herbert H. Lehman Papers". 1965 (Box 313)
  - Printed -Articles by and About Cordier (Box 314)
  - Books by, with contributions or annotations by Cordier (Box 315)
  - Books about or citing Cordier (Box 316)
  - Articles and books inscribed to Cordier (Box 317)
  - Books inscribed to Cordier (Box 318-324)
  - U.N. Book inscribed to Cordier (includes The Dag Hammarskjold Library) (Box 325)
  - U.N. Handbooks find Directories (Box 325)
  - Miscellaneous printed material about U.N. (Box 326)
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1944-1965 (Box 327)
  - Newspaper Clippings, Miscellaneous (Box 328)
  - Printed Miscellany (Box 329)
  - Lists (superseded) of Cordier papers (Box 330)
  - Oversized Items (Box 330)
  - Catalogued items 7 (Box 330)
  - Uncatalogued pictures 1 Folder (Box 330)
  - Volumes 3 (Box 330)
  - Plaques 3 (Box 330)
  - Degrees and Honors 13 (Box 330)
  - Degrees and Honors (framed) 5 (Box 330)
  - Degrees and Honors (scrolls) 1 tube (Box 330)
  - Pictures (framed) 8 (Box 330)
  - Films 4 (Box 330)
  - Phonograph records 26 (individual 4 multi-record sets) (Box 330)
  - Plans (Rolls) 5 (Box 330)
- Series X: 1979 Addition
  - Trip, 5-6/1975. Interviews and related correspondence. Index added, 1982 (NOT TO BE USED WITHOUT PERMISSION OF'THE LIBRARIAN FOR RARE BOOKS AND MANUSCRIPTS) (Box 331)
  - Correspondence with publishers, Wilder Foote, and others, and miscellaneous items, 1961 -1975. Also Included: Death of a Stalwart: A Profile of Andrew W. Cordier by Doreen Geary, 1918. t.ms.,. 320p. (copy) (Requires Permission of the Librarian for Rare Books and Manuacripts) (Box 332)
- Series XI: 1980 Addition
  - Personal Letters (primarily to and from family), 1928-1966 (Box 333)
  - School and College Papers Notebooks, ca. 1928-1939, 1928-1975 "Southern France After the Albigensian Crusade" (Cordier dissertation) -1 volume (Box 334)
  - Europe Since the War, A. W. Cordier, 1936. 2 mimeograph volumes. (Box 335)
  - General Files: (Box 336)
    - Birth and Marriage Certificates (Box 336)
    - Certificates and Documents (Box 336)
    - Miscellaneous Condolences and Tributes, 1915 (Box 336)
    - Cordier, Dorothy B. Scholarship Fund Correspondence (Box 336)
    - Miscellaneous, 1946-1975 (Box 336)
    - Engagements, 1956-1962, (3 Folders) (Box 336)
    - Honors Japan Trip, 1972 (Box 336)
    - MacMurray College Address, 3 June 1956 (Box 336)
    - Manuscripts and Miscellaneous Items (Box 336)
  - Condolence Letters, 1972 (Box 337)
  - Photographs (Box 338)
  - Printed Material (Box 338)
  - Awards and Plaques (Box 339-341)
  - Oversize Material (Box 339-341)
  - Cataloged items (7) (Box 339-341)
  - Uncataloged pictures (1 Folder) (Box 339-341)
  - Volumes (3) (Box 339-341)
  - Plaques (3) (Box 339-341)
  - Degrees and Honors (13) (Box 339-341)
  - Degrees and Honors (Framed)(5) (Box 339-341)
  - Degrees and Honors (scrolls)(1 tube) (Box 339-341)
  - Pictures (frames) (8) (Box 339-341)
  - Films (4) (Box 339-341)
  - Phonograph records (26 individual) (Box 339-341)
  - Phonograph records (4 multi-record sets) (Box 339-341)
  - Plans (rolls) (5) (Box 339-341)
- Supplement to Cordier register (6,3/03)
  Boxes 235 and 236 (metal card files) have been reboxed in document boxes. Box 235 has become Boxes 235A and 235B, and Box 236 is now Boxes 236A and 236B
  - UN Files --Index to Public Papers of the Secretaries:
    - Trygve Lie (Box 235A)
    - Dag Hammarskjold (Box 235B)
    - U Thant (Box 236A)
    - Kurt Waldheim (Box 236B)
  - Restricted UN Files Restricted material removed from other Boxes:
    - UN Files --Restricted items removed from Boxes 78,81,82,95,96, 101, 112, 114, 118-120 and 121­123 (Box 342)
    - UN Files --Restricted items removed from Boxes 124, 125,129 and 131-136. (Box 343)
    - UN Files --Restricted items removed from Boxes 137, 157-163, 179, 183.and 189. (Box 344)
    - UN Files --Restricted items removed from Boxes 191-196. (Box 345)
    - UN Files --Restricted items removed from Boxes 197 and 202. (Box 346)